Alexandre TANGUY

Engineering manager

Head of IT technical teams and projects with a network and security engineer background.

- What I (love to) do: management of teams, encouraging excellence, lead by example, being data-driven and customer-oriented, collect of requirements.
- What I am not: a software engineer. This is important to have in mind that I don't do software development myself.







Who am I and what am I looking for?

Information technology engineer and manager, 33 years old, father of 2, living in Bordeaux, France.

Passionate by the tech universe, project and human management.

After 7 years in the tech field as a network and security engineer – where I learned lots of things and grew up as an engineer and a human being – I understood that I was happier and more efficient leading a team and helping its members to grow.

I seized the opportuny offered by OVHcloud to manage one – and then two – teams of software engineers.

Today, I love this mission and I am eager to continue in a challenging (new?) environment with great ambition, to build strong teams and achieve big projects.

Professional experience

Engineering Manager @ OVHcloud in Bordeaux (January 2020 - Present)
Team leader of the Network Data squad, composed of the Network Observability and the Network IPAM teams.

- The *Network Observability* team (5 to 8 engineers) has the mission to design, develop, deploy and maintain internal applications to monitor tens of thousands of network devices:
 - Metrics: 50M+ timeseries / 1M+ datapoint per second
 - Logs: 25M+ log messages per day
 - ICMP requests/packets: 18M+ packets per minute
 - Lots of more specific applications in the portfolio (alerts routing, path discovery, BUM collector, etc.)
- The Network IP Management (IPAM) team (2 to 3 engineers) is in charge of managing the OVHcloud IP addresses plan and its growth. This team also develops every tools and backend required to allow OVHcloud squads and units to use, reserve, attribute and release IP addresses. She is also in close relation with the external IP providers (RIPE, ARIN, APNIC).
- Point of contact for other teams and PU about Network observability and IP related topics
- Follow-up on projects and program, estimation of required workload, planification
- Creation of rolling roadmaps with Program managers support over 12 months
- Agile methodology implementation and animation: sprint planning, daily, sprint review, retrospective, etc.

Notable projects (leading, not writing code):

- Build a MAC addresses collector at scale and processing pipeline to help operational teams locate servers in a big VXLAN network (Kotlin/Kubernetes/S3/Dremio)
- SNMP/API/Telemetry distributed metrics polling at scale (java)
- Implement a workflow processing tool to filter and route alerts from any source (our applications) towards many outputs (kafka, API, Opsgenie, etc.)
- Maintain and improve an ICMP Scanner application created by the team: end-to-end monitoring system sending ICMP packets towards +4 millions IPs every 15s and processing the result
- Build a complete application with GO workers deployed on network devices to discover and graph every network paths (ECMP compatible) between two servers in the OVHcloud

Network Engineer @ OVHcloud in Bordeaux (Mars 2018 - January 2020) Member of the Network Design Datacenter team, I was in charge of the vRack product design and projects.

- In charge of the design of network products: vRack, datacenter and (during one year) backbone
- In charge of R&D and deployment on datacenter infrastructure projects: IP failover routed in the vRack, OVHcloud Connect, vRack
- Support of the Network Operations team when issue on the perimeter
- Technologies: BGP, VXLAN, ECMP, Cisco and Arista devices, YAML/JSON

Network and Security Engineer @ Cdiscount in Bordeaux (December 2015 - Mars 2018) Member of the Security team during 1 year and then moved to the SRE team for 1 year (internal move-up).

- In charge of the network and security infrastructure operations (L3)
- In charge of the improvement and evolution of the network and security infrastructure, working in/with the Security team
- Part of the PCIDSS / SOX compliance and annual certification
- **Technologies:** Cisco ACI, Checkpoint firewalls, F5 loadbalancers, Citrix Netscaler, RIP/OSPF/VLAN

Network and Security Engineer @ Rothschild & Co in Paris (February 2015 - November 2015) Member of the Network and Security team, as a project lead of the "IT migration of internal ressources to HP Enterprises", and as Net/Sec engineer.

- In charge of the network and security operations (support of the team lead)
- Point of contact and follow-up of the externalisation project
- Technologies: Cisco Catalyst, Checkpoint firewalls, F5 loadbalancers, RIP/OSPF/VLAN

Network and Security Engineer @ Société Générale in Paris (January 2013 - February 2015) Member of one of the Network and Security team in charge of FranFinance and La Banque Postale Financement.

- In charge of infrastructure operations (75%)
- In charge of infrastructure improvement and migration projects (25%)
- Technologies: Cisco Catalyst, Checkpoint firewalls, Citrix Netscaler

Network and Security Engineer @ Crédit Agricole - CA Technologies & Services in Lyon (July 2011 - November 2012)
Internship and then "contrat de professionnalisation"

- Assistant of the project lead of the "Migration X25" project
- Network L3 operations

Education and languages

- January 2015: CCNA v2 certification (200-120). Result: 958/1000
- 2012: **TOEIC 940/990**
- 2007 2012: SUPINFO Engineer in IT technologies (french Bac+5 Master II niveau 1)
- June 2007: BAC S specialty mathematics (Baccalauréat Scientifique spécialité Mathématiques)

Activities and interests

- **Hobbies**: reading (sci-fi, fantasy, classical, history), photography, music listening (jazz and electronic)
- Sports: climbing/bouldering, running, cycling, hiking
- **Volunteering**: member of the french Red-Cross (Croix-Rouge française) from 2013 to 2015 as a rescuer (PSE2) and local director